Hello there you beautiful people.
No it's time to put added data structure skills to the test by making a cinema simulator.
So this project is going to let users choose from a range of films and the user will pick a film and
then the program will ask them for their age.
If they're old enough to watch the film and there are enough seats available then the program will let
them use a book to see the film.
If not the program will tell them that they're too young or there's nine of seats available or whenever
.
So pretty cool right now by the end of this project.
You should have a great understanding of how variables logic and data structures all tied together to
build programs.
So I can't wait to get started.
Let's jump right in.
So first of all as I'm sure you know first thing we're going to do is create a new script.
We're going to save that on the desktop Python Bible cinema doppie.
Why save that.
Maximize it.
And we're all good to go.
Right.
So first we're going to create some kind of data structure to store information about our films.
Now I'm going to use a dictionary for this.
As each film is going to be its own key and have its own data.
So since this current video is being filmed in about the middle of 2016 I'm just going to make you a
list of some of the current films with random ages and seat numbers.
But feel free to create your own dictionary with any films that you want.
So the dictionary is going to store the age rating for the film and also the number of seats left.
Let's make a dictionary called films and I'm going to create it like LA.
Okay now inside here I'm going to put Finding Dory 3.
So they have the the the age for this I'm going to say is three and there are five tickets.
Let's say so and then you go have born.
Pretty sure he's in the cinema.
Eighteen and five.
Tarzan
Ghostbusters.
Okay so let's put that in there 12 and 5.
Okay so there we go.
We've got our dictionary of films.
Obviously you can add as many as you want and mix and match for what you desire.
Girl leave it with those few.
So I'm going to do a little cheat again now and I'm going use a while loop.
So this program is going to run over and over again just like we did for Travis.
But don't worry we're going to cover loops in detail in the next section shula's Bear with me for now
.
Just going to type while True.
And now put our code inside here okay.
So now we need to ask the user what film they want to watch.
So there's a micro challenge.
Go ahead and ask the user what film they want to watch using the input function and store that choice
in a variable called choice.
You know the drill.
Pause the video have a go and come back to see how you did.
So how did you get on.
I'd have done it like this and it's done in here type choice equals input.
What film would you like to watch that and just in case the enter some white space.
I'm just going to strip it off right there.
And also actually because as you can see every single one of the films that I've put here in a key every
word starts with a capital letter.
Right.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to use the title string method as well to convert whatever they
put into title case so there every If they enter Ghostbusters then Ghost will start with a capital G
and bust as we start with capital B regardless of how you know they might type it themselves.
So what is going to do that right there.
Now if you follow along with this and if you got back early or you've just been following along then
you're doing absolutely brilliantly because now we're going to start kicking off to more hard core things
.
Okay so now we need to check if the film that the user has chosen in choice is in the list of films
Now this is very easy to do just by using the in keyword right.
So if let's just check if choice in films.
Now actually I'm just going to introduce you to the pass Keyword the passkey word basically just tells
python.
Just move on.
OK.
This is just a blank place holder.
We're not going to actually write the code in here yet.
I'm just building the the structure.
So if the choice is in there just pass and do nothing or otherwise print we don't have that film.
And I'm going to make it build suspense.
So much should be pretty good like that.
Now when we run it like we run it I'm going to say Tarzan is not going to do anything.
Rochas are in it found the film but it just saw pass and went back around the loop.
Now if we run it again and say Rocky 7 and so then we don't have that film.
So our logic is working which is brilliant.
Okay so let's stop this thing running.
The next thing we've got to do is we've got to check whether the user is old enough to watch the film
.
So what I can do is if the choice is in the films room if the choices they're winning to check whether
the use is old enough of say age equals input.
How old are you.
Okay.
And I'm going to strip whatever comes off from that.
So how can we take whatever they put out and compare it with the age that's in here.
Well first of all we actually need to make sure that age is a number never you remember.
When I was talking over the input function it always brings in a string.
Okay it even if you type a number it saves it as a string.
So to convert all of this into an integer we to actually cast it from a string into an integer.
So here we get a string we strip any white space off it and then we convert that whole thing into an
integer indoor into a number and save that in the age now.
Now what we need to check is if that age is greater than or equal to the age requirement for the film
.
So how do we know that.
Well we go in the film's dictionary look up the film that they chose.
So let's say they entered Tarzan wrote this this if we look up the key of Tarzan it's going to give
us back this list.
Now the age is the first element in that list.
So I'm going to type in index zero.
So we're looking up the choice as a key in the films.
Now you know it makes sense why we had to get it in Title Case and we had to strip everything off and
once we've got the value which will be this this list we're going to look up the first element in it
which corresponds to the age and if their age is greater than or equal to that then we're going to print
.
Enjoy the film.
OK.
We'll come onto tickets and a little bit.
But otherwise if they're not old enough we'll get a print.
You are too young to see that film.
Okay so let's have a look.
Let's have a look at how that works.
So what film would you like to watch.
So say we want to watch Tarzan.
How old are you.
Let's say I'm 5 year old.
You're too young to see that film.
Okay so let's say if we won or what Tarzan again let's say now I'm ninety nine.
Enjoy the film right so that works absolutely fine right there.
So take another example.
Let's say if we want to watch Finding Dory.
How old are you.
I want I am say nine years old.
Enjoy the film.
That works fine as well.
So let's cancel that out and depressing Control see.
And now we need to build the bit where it checks the number of tickets.
So to check whether there are enough tickets instead of just letting them you know enjoy the film straight
away after checking their age.
I'm going to write here check check user age in here.
Wait a minute.
Just with a comment.
Check user age now in here.
We'll go to check check enough seats.
Right.
So if how do we how do we know the number of seats.
Well the number of seats is this is the second element.
So if the films of that choice.
Yes.
This is the the Basically this list for the corresponding film.
If the seats of that which is element 1 is greater than or equal or bet we can just say if that's greater
than zero right then they will then will get to tell them enjoy the film.
We tell them enjoy the film and we're going to subtract one from the number of tickets left.
So films choice 1.
Not messing up films of choice one equals films of choice one minus one.
Okay.
So were taking whatever the value is for the number of tickets and we're subtracting one from it then
saving it back in there another way that we can do this to make it a bit clearer.
We could say numb seats equals films of choice 1 Okay.
And if not seats is greater than zero.
They're going to say enjoy the film.
I'm numb.
Seats is going to become numb seats minus one.
But actually that bit won't work.
Actually no.
We do need to change that film.
Films choice it's going to become
we did need to keep that the way that it was before.
So we're just overwriting the number of seats right there.
And that's pretty much it to be honest I think you guys lensless What's that work.
So there's always five seats right.
So what film joy to watch was cause a Tarzan cause diseases to spell.
How old are you.
Let's say three.
You you're too young to see that film.
Oh OK.
If I'm Tarzan again watch in it.
How old are you.
I am 50.
OK.
So there should be four tickets Tarzan.
I'm 15.
Oh OK.
No there should be three tickets Tarzan.
I'm 15.
Now there should be two tickets was 15.
One ticket Tarzan 15.
This down now there should be no tickets left Tarzan 15.
And it actually didn't say enjoy the film.
Okay.
You did you know the way that we ran our tickets and it didn't say enjoy the film.
We put in just another message in here.
If number of seats is greater than zero then do all that.
Else.
Print.
Sorry.
We are sold out now.
You think you can trust me that that works.
You can run the code yourself.
But trust me that's going to that's going to work fine.
One thing that I do want to highlight though.
Can you see the way that we've got if statements inside of if statements inside of if statements and
all sorts of stuff going on there the way the python works to have something inside something else is
you can see that it's indenting it.
I mentioned this a bit earlier in the course but it makes more sense here.
There's a certain amount of indenting going on and this saves you from having to type loads of brackets
and loads of stuff like that load and which makes the code quite ugly.
Like in programs like Java and C and things like that.
But you do have to have the indentation.
Otherwise Python just won't work.
It won't be able to tell what's inside of something else.
So make sure you get a indentation right.
Idol's going to do it for you pretty much.
I mean if you just go to the end of the line and press enter you can see whether it's automatically
indented.
And if I told another if it's going to automatically indented again.
So you know idle's going to help you out with these things.
But that does need to be right so if your code's not working and it says indentation error or something
like that that's the problem.
But awesome.
I mean do you see how quick that was.
We've just built a program that can actually check whether a user is old enough to watch a film and
whether there are enough seats left in the system.
Also updates itself when someone books a film and also reduces the number of seats by one and when someone
purchases a ticket.
If you understood all of that and followed along and did it yourself you should be so proud of yourself
honestly.
You're learning so much and you should share this victory with your friends so they can celebrate along
with you.
This is a really big achievement.
I mean look at it man.
Looking at you've got dictionaries strings less while lubes if statements and user input updating variables
conditions logic all that stuff in there you should be so proud of yourself.
Honestly I'm very proud of you as well.
Now in this project we've applied data structures to create an assortment of films use plenty of logic
data type conversions converting here we've been casting and basically using everything since the start
of the cause into a functional program.
And with that now we're going to end on a high and come to the end of this section of the course on
data structures as you've like learned so much with this section of the course lets us have a quick
recap in the next video to go over what we've learned just to make sure it all sticks and I'll see you
in the next video.