Hello there you beautiful people.
And welcome to the review lecture for this section on Python.
Data Structures now in this sorrowful section of the course were really covered a lot and hopefully
have you've gotten a very powerful tool that you can using your programs to structure your data and
manipulate it.
Really however you want.
We started off by looking at lists the most common type of data structure in Python.
First you learn the basics.
And so what the list is and how to create one after that you learn the list can hold different types
of data.
And the lists are an Iterable data type which means they can be broken up into little pieces called
elements.
Each element is accessible via an index and you learn how to use indexes to access certain elements
and also how to take slices through your lists to access multiple elements at once.
Then we stepped it up a gear and you learn how to use lists to create multi-dimensional data structures
like tables and use indexes like coordinates to access certain rows and columns.
You only need this all the time but it might come in useful when you want to make a Rubik's Cube solver
or something like that.
So after that you built Travis the ridiculous but totally lovable secuity robot.
In that project you heard all about how to add items to a list and how to delete them from a list.
You learned how data structures can be combined with logic systems and you also introduce to the.
In keyword word which checks whether some value is in an Iterable data type.
You also learned about the non data type which she learned how to manage their use of lists methods
correctly so that you don't accidentally delete your data.
After that we started talking all about tuples.
You learn that tools are basically like lists except that they're immutable which means they cannot
be changed once you have created them.
And this keeps your data safe at the expense of some flexibility.
You know how to create two balls and your cylinder call trick called multiple assignment where you can
create multiple variables with just one line of code.
After that we moved on to the dictionary data type.
Now dictionaries are a glorious data type that allow us to look at values with easy to remember keys
.
You made a mini database of students and stored their ages under their names.
You don't have to add new keys to dictionaries head update their values and how to delete them.
You also learned about the keys values and items methods for dictionaries to get addiction's keys values
and items respectively and also how to get this information in list format using the list function.
Now if all of that wasn't enough yourself had had to put lists and even dictionaries inside of dictionaries
which gave your dictionaries superpower's basically.
We use this to store not only a student's name but also their age their student I.D. and their grade
.
Then finally we combine all of the stuff we've learned so far in the course to make a cinema booking
system.
This program combined everything we know so far about variables numbers strings logic and data structures
to really show off your skills as a python pro.
So bravo.
This section has really brought a lot of new skills to the table and I hope you really let these concepts
sink in.
As they'll come in useful time and time and time and time and time again.
Oh sorry was I repeating myself words probably because the next section of the Course is on loops loops
help to automate the task of programming itself and are a critical piece of every programming tool kit
loops l.a. to do in one line of code.
What might take hundreds or thousands or even millions of lines of code to do otherwise and Python makes
them crazily easy to do.
Now you're not going to want to miss this so see you in the next video.