Hello there you beautiful people.
And welcome to the e-mail slicer project.
Well we're going to learn all about slicing up strings now slicing is a very useful thing that Python
allows us to do.
And it's simplicity really sets it apart from other programming languages.
Now in this project we're going to create an e-mail slicer.
There were ask someone for their email address and it will tell them what their username is and tell
them who their email account is held with or their domain name which will in a very basic way anyway
.
So before all of that in this lecture I'm going to explain to you what slices are and I'm sure you'll
agree.
By the end of it they're super awesome.
And by the end of the lecture you'll know how to chop strings up to use just the information you want
.
So let's get into it.
So what is a slice.
Well a slice as you might imagine is just a small piece of something larger.
Now for this to make any sense we need to take a fresh look at what strings actually are.
A string is basically a bunch of characters and letters that are strung together.
So let's say if I have the string.
A B C D E F G.
1.
One two three four five and six.
Okay.
So here we have a bunch of letters and numbers that are strung together to make a string.
Now in Python strings are an Iterable datatype.
Now what the hell does that mean.
Well when something is Iterable it means you can go step by step along it until you get to the end Iterable
means you can go step by step along it until you get to the end.
Now each of these steps is called an element so there would be one step.
There's another step.
There's another step and each of those are elements of the string.
Now each element also has a number that refers to its position.
So this number is called an index and by using the index you can get to the element so by using the
index you get to the element.
Now these index numbers start at zero.
That means the first element is indexed zero.
The second element is index 1.
The third element is indexed to be indexed for our sorry index three must be index for index 5 and so
on.
So the best way to show you this is if we had an example a rather long word so let's just say we have
word equals Supercalifragilistic XP hourly doges.
Okay so it's just so valla about now.
If you've ever watched Mary Poppins then that word will make sense.
If not Go ahead watch Mary Poppins.
No we just want the first letter of this the letter S then.
We just have to take the first index or index zero probably the best way to say is the 0 4 index of
the string so we do that by typing word which is the name of the variable.
Then opening up a spear a pair of square brackets.
And inside here we type the number of the index that we want.
So we want the 0 0 index so we type 0 and that's going to give us S..
Now even though that I've just technically sliced out the letter S the original data is still unchanged
.
So as you can see I sliced o ass but it's still there in the original.
Variable.
And that's because strings are immutable meaning they cannot be changed.
So if you wanted to say it correctly I mean you could say that strings are an immutable Iterable datatype
because they can't be changed and you can iterate over each element so as a micro challenge for you
.
I want you to see whether you can just go ahead and pull out the letter P case or use a just a mini
slice to take out this letter P here from the string.
So how do you get on the way that I do it.
AK is we know that this is the 0 4 index.
This is the first index and this is the second index right.
So what we do is type a word of two.
And that's going to give us the letter P.
So what if you wanted to take more than one letter.
Well for this we use a slice okay.
These will just kind of picking out little elements here and there but if you want to take out a proper
slice from the variable then this is how we do it.
So the format of a slice is like this.
You type a variable name.
Okay then you put some square brackets.
You put the index you want to start up the index you want to go to and the step in between each element
you want to select.
So you have a variable name.
In our case this would be word.
And let's say we wanted to take from this day we just wanted to take the word super.
Okay well we want to start from Index zero because that's the letter S.
Now the tricky part comes when you have end here.
So we want are right we want to be nothing at 0 1 2 3 4.
This is indexed for.
But the way the end works is it is the you you put in the index of where you want to go to.
OK.
So if we wanted to go up to.
We want if we wanted our We'd have to go up to the letter C right but not including it.
So to take this way we have to go up to here.
Since here this letter C has index of 0 1 2 3 4 5 we put in there five.
And we want every letter.
So we put one as the step.
So let's watch that now.
We see we get out the word super.
We started at index 0 and included that one.
And we went up to but not including the letter C so that the letter C was indexed five.
So we put that there.
We didn't want that we just want to go up to it and we wanted to go in one element every time.
So if I just just to show you what the steptoe's if I put two here.
You see we get S P R because this goes zero go up to gets P gook to GA.
Okay.
That's what the steps are doing.
But one was taking every single one.
So as a micro challenge for you then I want you to go ahead and create a slice that will take out the
word callee.
Here Ill take that out and print that to the screen.
So go ahead pause the video now and try to use a slice to take out the word calleigh from word.
So how do you get on did you manage it.
Well here's the way that I have gone about it I would know that the letter C is at index 0 1 2 3 4 5
.
So I'd put that as the start and I'd want to go up to the letter F and the letter f is 0 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 9 a case I put nine in there and I want every girl every one so I put a step one and you see we
get calleigh out.
So if you got that then absolutely fantastic you're really getting ahead with with strings like this
.
Now there are some shortcuts to using string which are super useful.
So let's say we wanted to just take from the letter C all the way to the end for that all we have to
do is type a word.
Then the start was going to be five because that's where C is right and C is index 5.
Then just type a colon and Python is now going to automatically assume that I want from 5 all the way
to the end which is what we see here pretty handy right.
So here's another shortcut.
What if I wanted to go from calleigh again from courtesy all the way to the end.
But in steps of too well for that I just type the word mamasa the way word five and then just type another
coal on and to see you can see that we've left the end blank here because it goes start.
END.
Step right we've left end blank.
We didn't tell it where to end.
So it's going to assume that to go all the way to the end.
But in steps of two and we're going to see that it does that it goes C then L then F then a C.
Now then for the hey are you an R and T and all the way all the way until the end.
So that's a really useful trick as well.
So what if we wanted everything up to index 7 let's say.
So this is indexed 5 6 and 7 so everything up until the L..
But not including it.
So for that we would type a word leaves start blank and type seven just like that.
And that is going to give us everything up to index 7.
So since index 7 is that L..
We're going to go up to L. But not include it.
I guess that's something you've got to be aware of when using slices.
It's always up to but not including if we wanted the L. we'd have to do opt to 8 which is the one after
the L right so that would be that to give to get us the other.
So we go up a few lines you saw that we typed 0 to 5 insteps of 1 to get super right.
And that that war that will work fine.
But no with our shortcuts all we've got to do is type word coal on five like that because zero it's
going to assume you want to start here at zero and it's going to assume you want steps of one.
If I just do that we're going to get super straight away see you see just how much easier I is.
Now this is super useful.
You can actually reverse a string.
Well the steps can actually be negative.
Right.
And we can use this to reverse a string.
So if I did word and I just did coal on coal on minus 1.
Basically what that's going to say is glow from the end to the start in steps of minus one.
And if I do that we're going to see that we've actually just reversed the whole string in just one line
of code.
Now doing that in any other programming languages is a monster really so doing.
Being able to do that in such a simple way is a really powerful trick.
So you know understand the basics of how to take slices right.
We know that strings have basically an Iterable datatype which means they're made up of little elements
and each of these little elements has an index that starts from zero.
That you can use to access that element.
And when you take a slice you put the starting element here.
The starting date index sorry then the the where you want to go up to.
And then the step and we also know a few short cuts here and there but we have a main issue in that
the way that I've been doing it so far is error prone.
I'm kind of counting up the index from the beginning and if there can be time consuming and I can make
errors write it all it takes it for me to count one number wrong and I've messed the whole thing up
.
So what I'm going to show you in the next video is how to pretty much automate this process right using
Python's index function which is a massively powerful trick when using strings.
So I will show you that in the next video.
In the interest of time.
So I ask you that.