Hello there you beautiful people.
So this is just another quick video about some of the some useful tricks you can do when you're dealing
with slices.
The first thing I want to show you is you don't have to count from the very beginning in order to get
up to where you want to go.
So you can actually count from this end.
So let's say I wanted you.
Okay.
I could count up 0 1 2 3 4 5 all the way up until you right.
Or I could do word and count back from the other end.
So this value here is actually index minus one.
So you would be index minus two.
Okay.
And they see we get you less safe we wanted this see they'll be minus one minus two minus three minus
four minus five word minus five should give us C..
And it does.
So this is a nice short cut.
You don't have to count all the way from from this and you can can from this and remembering that the
very end value is minus one.
So if you want the very end value you just type minus one and it's going to give us s at the end.
But this doesn't solve the actual issue which is that we're still counting right in our head as a human
being which can make mistakes.
What we want to do is to leverage the power of the computer to do all the counting for us and for that
we're going to use the index function.
So let's say for example I wanted to just take the word calleigh out what I could do is I could type
a word.
And I want where calleigh starts so I could type in here word dot index of callee.
Okay.
Because where starts.
Let me just show you actually I mean just make it a bit simpler.
Index sorry word dot index of calleigh is going to give us five because cow he starts at index five
right 0 1 2 3 4 5 so what.
And we want to go all the way up to fragile.
Right.
So fragile starts at index word dot index.
Fragile is going to give us 9.
So what I could do is to have a word then the first where I want to start at the index of where calleigh
starts and I want to go up to where fragile starts in steps of one by default.
And it's going to give me out callee because it's going to go from where he starts to where the next
to where raji stars and that he's going to pull that out.
So using indexes using the index function is a massive shocker right.
I mean it makes life so much easier to do it that way.
Let's say if we wanted to take out the word doescher.
Okay let's say want to take this out.
All we've got to do is do word of word dot index doescher which is where it starts.
Right.
And I want to go from there to the end just to put a coal on.
It's going to seem odd to go to the end and pull it out which is fantastic.
If I wanted to get out fragile stick around so I just do word of word dark index gradualist stick all
the way up to where I mean to be honest with you.
I could just do XP right word dot index XP fragileness because I could I could just write XP and oceans
are Uecker straight XP.
Now one thing you do have to bear in mind is that index only returns the first instance of that phrase
that you're searching for.
So if I if I wanted to get fragileness to go again.
Okay let's say I went like this and I wanted to go up to word dot index of E.
I don't think that will work.
It won't work right.
It obviously was an empty string.
And the reason is because index the index of E it finds the first E which is over here.
Not this one.
So if you wanted this one you need to say where you know something longer starts XP or XP and oceanus
or something that lets another.
You definitely want this one rather than the first day which is what causes this error here.
So that's something to bear in mind also.
So that's pretty much all there is to slicing to be fair pretty easy right.
So I just have a quick recap of what we've learned in the past two videos just to make sure we've got
everything down before we head into the slicer project.
So we learned that strings are an Iterable immutable datatype and the fact that they are Iterable means
that you can access individual elements from the string.
Each element is given its own index and these start from the number zero and you use that index to access
the element.
You also learn how to take slices from a string and how to take individual elements out yourself and
a short cut for use in the index for by using the index function.
They can take a lot of the hard work of doing this out for us.
Overall you've got a pretty good understanding of what slices are and how to create them by now.
So up next we've got a quick quiz and coding challenge to check that you fully understood what slices
are.
And after that we're going to build our e-mail slicer.
So good luck in the quiz and the coding challenge which you're going to need in order to get some practice
.
Make sure you got it down and then I'll see you in the next video.