Ello there you beautiful people.
And in this lecture we're going to create the e-mail slicer.
So I hope you're excited.
This project going to tied together.
Everything we've learned about strings in this section.
So it is gathering user input slicing string formatting and even the occasional string method.
So basically how this is going to work is that we're going to ask the user for their e-mail address
using the input function.
After that we're going to slice the e-mail address for the user name and the email domain name and the
user name is what is before the at symbol and the domain name is what's after the at symbol.
In case you're wondering so we're going to use string formatting to output the user a message that tells
in their user name and their domain name.
Pretty cool right.
So after this ledger you have to understand how each of the different pieces regarding strings fits
together and you also can have built another core python program to prove it.
Let's get started.
So the first thing I'm going to do is create another script so go far new file save this on the desktop
in the python Bible and I'm going to call this slice a dot P Y.
And when I maximize this were all good to go.
So I'm going to use Python comments to help give us a bit of an outline for what we're going to do in
the project.
The first thing we're going to do is to get the user's email address.
So get user e-mail address then we're going to slice out the user name slice out user name we'll go
to slice out the domain name slice demesne name we'll go to format some kind of output message so format
message and then was going to display the output message.
So display output message.
Awesome.
That's easy enough right.
All right so now that we've planned though our project Let's go follow the checklist and get the user's
email address nef for this.
As you'll recall to get a to get a input from a user willing to use the input function.
So we're going to call whatever the input is a variable called e-mail and use the input function by
asking them a question.
What is your e-mail address just like that.
I'm also going just going to capitalize it to make sure a little bit nicer.
Now the user may very well type in their e-mail address and then accidentally press a space or something
like that which we don't want inside of our input.
So whatever the user inputs were going to strip away all of the blank spaces from it using the strip
string method.
So while up there we are.
There's the first step of the project done.
So a step number two we need to slice out the user name.
Now the user name is everything up to the at symbol.
So if there you know for example if there you if their e-mail was like Now Barb Doe at finger dot com
then their username would be Bob Dole and the domain there would be Thank you doctor.
Okay so which one the usenet with them in it which is everything.
Up until the at symbol.
So I want you to create a variable called user and using the index function and a slice.
I want you to take a slice of the e-mail variable and which is which corresponds to the to their email
address.
It could be any e-mail address.
So I want you to take use the index function to take a slice up until the at symbol and save that in
the variable called user.
So you know the drop pause the video now and come back when you're done with up to see how you did.
So how do you get on.
This is the way that I'd have gone about doing it.
I would.
Well let me just do this.
I would have created a variable called user and assigned it the value of a slice from e-mail starting
at the beginning opened till the index of the at symbol.
Okay.
So everything up to the at symbol is going to be saved in the user variable.
Nice and easy.
All right so now we need to get the domain name which is everything after the at symbol.
So there's another micro challenge I want you to use slices again to store in a variable called Domain
everything after the at symbol in that email variable.
So go ahead now and pause the video and give that a go try to get everything after the at symbol not
including the outer symbol.
Bear in mind everything after the at symbol all the way until the end of the string and then come back
to see how you did.
How did you know did you get on all right.
There's a bit tricky right.
So the way that I have done it is I'd have create the variable called domain and other set that equal
to a slice from email.
But we want to go from we want to take everything after the V out symbol right.
So the way that I do that is I take the index of the at symbol like that but we don't want to start
there because if we start there then what's going to happen is it's going to include the at symbol.
So I want to take from that index plus one.
I want to go to the one after it then just use a colon to go all the way up until the end of the string
.
So this is the way that I have done it.
Astarte is the index of the of the at symbol plus one.
So it's one after it.
So if the index was five then this would give a six.
She one after.
And then we'd use the coal on to give us a short cut to go all the way until the end of the stream.
And that's going to get us there domain name.
All right.
The next step is to create a the output message and the output message is going to look something like
this.
I'm going to have outputs equals your user name is blank and your domain name is blank.
Now I want you to at the end of this string here to use the Format function to put in the first place
the username and in the second place the domain name which we've taken out from here so is a micro try
.
Use the Format function to put the user name in here the domain name in here then come back to see how
you did.
So hopefully that went well for you.
This is the way that I'd have done it I'd have just typed dot format because format is again a string
method and I'm going to put in the first thing user because that's what holds I use an and then I'm
going to put a comma.
And after that I'm going to put domain because domain holds our domain name and that should be that
so.
Now all we've got to do is print out the output message right.
So print output.
Now when I save and run the lesher see how this works.
Let's.
Okay so what's your e-mail address.
Let's say we have super awesome name at galactic mail dot com right.
This doesn't exist by the way and if it does and you're watching this then you're the unluckiest person
alive.
But anyway if I do that it's going to say your username is super awesome name and your domain name is
galactic mail dot.com.
Hey.
So there we are we managed to slice up an email address into it a user name and its domain name using
Python slices.
Well done.
I bet you mean you should probably give yourself a proper pat on the back if you follow through this
and understand everything and feel now that you have Python strings down pat.
You have Python strings under your belt and you're a master of them.
So Welldone know we've covered a lot in this section of the course and as usual I'm just going to have
a quick recap in the next video of what we've learned to prime you for the next exciting section of
the course on logic.
So congratulations once again on following through this project and being able to create an e-mail slicer
.
I'll see the next video for a recap and then will move on to learn all about logic so I'll see you in
the next video.