Wow we've really covered a lot in this section and a python Bible on strings.
Now in this lecture I just want to make a quick review of what we've covered and also give you a little
taster of what's coming up in the next section.
So after this lecture you'll be feeling really proud of yourself and what you've learned about strings
and hopefully you'll be rather excited for the next section of the Gores on logic which is where all
the really cool stuff happens.
But I won't spoil anything Yeah.
Let's do our review.
We started off by looking at what strings are and how we can make them.
We saw that there are three main ways single quotes double quotes and triple quotes.
Now Python gives us this many ways because it gives us plenty of flexibility when making strings and
also stops our strings from breaking.
When we use certain punctuation.
Next you learned how to be a string mechanic.
By learning how to fix strings if they do get broken and after that you created the legendary hello
world program which entered you into the official realm of Python programmers.
Congratulations.
Welcome to the club.
After that you then sailed through a couple of coding challenges which checked your understanding and
you were then met with a second project of the course the helo you program.
We started off by showing you how to use Python's comments to structure your code and keep your mind
organized and focused on the task at hand.
Next you learned how to take a user's input and store it in variables to be use later in your program
and you then learn how to process these variables and create useful output messages using string concatenation
and string formatting.
You also learned how some data types are incompatible I can't simply be concatenated together like strings
and numbers.
You don't have to resolve problems with data.
Think about Habibti like this.
But learning how to convert or cast from one data type to another.
After that you sailed through another two coding challenges and then you learned all about string methods
.
First you learn what string methods are and how to use them.
Then we went through many useful functions that can do many useful things like finding the index of
a certain string inside another turning our string into upper case or count the amount of time a certain
piece of text appears and so on.
We also learn how to check whether a string was in the correct format with a few string methods as well
.
After that you learned all about slices.
You learn what they are how to use them and also a few shortcuts that makes using slices a dream.
You then had a quick quiz followed by a coding challenge to check your understanding and then we jumped
into a third project of the course that e-mails slicer in that project.
We combine all that we've learned so far to collect user input and store it in a string variable.
You then slice that variable into smaller pieces to get the user name and domain name from the email
address and finally use string formatting to create an output message for the user using the data that
they previously had provided you.
Well done well done well done to see you've done AMAZING.
So as you can see we've covered an incredible amount of stuff in this section and you should be feeling
super confident whenever you have to deal with text in Python now or in the future.
So well done.
The next section of course is one of my favorites at the moment.
Our programs are quite simple and they can only account for one possible route of action.
However life isn't like that and there are usually many possible routes that a user might take to deal
with all of these opportunities and possibilities.
We need a logic in the next section you're going to be learning all about logic in Python.
So the program can respond whichever the way the user chooses to go.
As you can see our Python programs are going to get a whole lot more bad ass so let's jump in and I'll
see you in the next video.